<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great loss and damage to England, by the transportation of wooll to forreign parts</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833942</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833942</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1833:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great loss and damage to England, by the transportation of wooll to forreign parts</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The great Loſs and Damage to <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND,</hi> by the Tranſportation of WOOLL to Forreign Parts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no King nor Prince in the World, known by experience or upon Record, that hath ſuch means to ſupport their Splendour and Greatneſs as his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> nor has any Country on Nation ſuch variety of Staple-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities within it ſelf, and in ſuch abundance; as hath the Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> So that if thoſe Advantages were duly improved, <hi>England</hi> might be a general Mart for the whole World; and then by conſequence be the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof. That thoſe Advantages are not improved is too too obvious to all that look into it; By the fore Complaints that are frequently made of the great Poverty, and decay thereof; And indeed (which is worſt of all) by that general deſperation of Spirit, which will not put forth a hand to help, ſupport, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Total deſolation of our Country, upon a prepoſſeſt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that all Endeavours will be rendred Fruitleſs and Abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration whereof, hath greatly prompted me (who muſt confeſs my ſelf the meaneſt of thouſands, more concerned) to uſe the utmoſt of my little skill and unwearied diligence (though but as the Woman's Mite) to the right management of ſo great an Undertaking, that the threatned Ruine of all may be prevented, and (if poſſible) ſome good part of that which is Loſt may be recovered. I ſhall confine my ſelf to thoſe things only whereof I have had not only credible Information, but a conſiderable (though a ſad) experimental knowledge; and in a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38421:2"/>more particular and eſpecial manner, that of the Manufacture of Wooll in <hi>England,</hi> which, amongſt Many, is the Richeſt Treaſure in his Majeſties Dominions, the flower, ſtrength, and ſinews of this Nation; a Band uniting the People into Societies for their own Utility: It is the Milk and Honey to the Grazier and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Farmer; the Gold and Spices of the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> to the Merchant, and Citizens; the continued ſupply of Bread to the Poor; and, in a word, the Exchequer of Wealth, and Staple of Protection to the whole, both abroad and at home; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of full merit to be had in perpetual remembrance, defence, and encouragement, for the moſt advantageous Improvements thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wool</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (before it was manufactured within it ſelf) was always of great account and eſteem abroad; ſufficiently teſtified unto, by the great amity which it begat, and for many hundred years (unviolably) maintained, between the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> only from the great benefit that (from that Commodity) did accrew to that People: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that the <hi>Engliſh Wools,</hi> they received at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, they returned again (through their Induſtrious Manufacture thereof) in Cloath at 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, to the great inriching of that State, both in the advancement of the Revenues of their Soveraign, and in a full employment (thereby) continued among the People; whereby the Merchants of this Nation were occaſioned, (as a People unwilling to be wholly diſpriviledged of ſo great a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit) to tranſport themſelves (with their Families, in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) into <hi>Flanders;</hi> from whence they held a conſtant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with moſt parts of the World. This continued without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion, between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Burgundy,</hi> until King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> made his mighty Conqueſt over <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and as a ſutable improvement of ſo great a mercy, did wiſely project, and alſo accompliſh, the manufacture of <hi>Wools</hi> within the Bowels of this Kingdom, to the great inriching of his own People, and alſo to the peopling of his new Conquered Dominions. The memory of whoſe wiſdome and care for his People, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be had in Remembrance by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, unto the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>The ſaid King having thus ſetled the manufacture of <hi>Wools</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38421:2"/>the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> confined it by a penal State, which (at firſt) reached not only to Goods, Chattels, and Lands, but alſo to Members, and Life it ſelf; but, in a ſhort time, repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the two latter thereof, continuing the other in its full force to remain to future Generations: Which exceeding great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the propriety of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade, hath now continued this Three Hundred years, by the vigilancy of the Kingdoms Monarchs, and the protection of its Laws, in the continued care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful execution thereof upon Offenders, with more than a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, to provide againſt the thirſting deſires of Foreiners to wreſt this Nations Priviledge (of ſo great a moment) out of <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands; which by the providence of God (through the care of our Anceſtors) has been (for many Ages) enjoyed by the Nation, as it is indeed its proper right. But ſo it is, that (for ſome years paſt) the diligence of Foreiners to enrich themſelves upon us, has ſo much exceeded our care to preſerve our ſelves, that it's now come to, if not beyond, a queſtion, Who have the greateſt benefit of the manufacture of <hi>Engliſh Wools,</hi> They who have no Right unto it, or, They to whom of Right it doth belong?</p>
            <p>That this is indeed ſo, will appear, by conſidering that not only <hi>Holland, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> have long ſucked the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sinews of our Trade; but <hi>France</hi> is likewiſe learning to be too hard for us, as is manifeſt by the great quantities of <hi>Wools,</hi> that (of late years) have been Tranſported from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> thither. How injurious it muſt be to us is alſo unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, if we conſider the conſequence thereof, which was (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion) much in the eye of our Anceſtors, as appears by what is above hinted in <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3ds.</hi> time, and in ſeveral Kings Reigns ſince.</p>
            <p>Every Pack of <hi>Wooll</hi> ſent to <hi>France,</hi> doth prevent us (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) of the benefit of the manufacture thereof, but of two Packs more beſides it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Thus; It being Combing, and Combed <hi>Wooll</hi> (for the moſt part) exported thither. The <hi>French</hi> (having no <hi>Wools</hi> of their own, but ſuch as are very coarſe) are not able to make Cloth, or fine Stuffs, without the conjunction of ours therewithal; there being none (to my beſt information) in all the World fit for that purpoſe (but ours only) except in North-<hi>Holland,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:38421:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38421:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38421:4"/>and that a ſmall quantity of fine Worſted <hi>Wooll;</hi> all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being likewiſe coarſe, but <hi>Spaniſh Wooll;</hi> and that much too fine, eſpecially for worſted Stuffs, and not in any wiſe fit for Combing; ſo that without <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Iriſh Wools,</hi> there can be no quantity of fine worſted Stuffs, nor a middle ſort of Cloth made in the whole World. Neither will any <hi>Wools</hi> be all mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> (for Cloth only), becauſe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> is with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of one nature; being formerly <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Sheep, though now much finer for the alteration of the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and the nature of the Land whereon it is fed, as by good Experience appeareth here in <hi>England,</hi> both near and at a further diſtance.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Exportation of <hi>Engliſh Wools</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> muſt of neceſſity be greatly prejudicial to this Nation; not only in the quantity ſent over, but alſo in the advantage which is thereby gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them to manufacture a double portion of their <hi>Wooll,</hi> (which (formerly) was little worth) into ſuch commodities as ſpoils us of the advantages of our proper Trades, not only thither, but alſo into other parts, <hi>viz.</hi> in theſe three Reſpects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Combed of the <hi>Engliſh Wooll</hi> makes Wooff for the Warps of the <hi>French Wooll</hi> (or rather of the Turkey Sheep) and ſo takes up (it may be) as much as the quantity above ſpecified, to every Pack of <hi>Engliſh Wooll,</hi> without which they can (only) with their <hi>Wooll,</hi> make Ruggs, and at the beſt, Cloth for Sea-men, and the like.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Their Combings or Pinnions, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſhort <hi>Wooll</hi> that's combed out of the Worſted, ſerves for their Linnen warp to make ſome of their Druggets, becauſe their Linnen being ſine ſpun, and coloured, is not diſcernable to all perſons, to be that we call <hi>Linſie-Wolſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The fineſt ſhort <hi>Engliſh Wooll</hi> is mixed with the loweſt of <hi>Spaniſh Wooll,</hi> called ſhort <hi>Wooll,</hi> for ſome of their beſt Druggets, that is wove upon worſted Chanies; and alſo for a middle ſort of Broad-cloth about 10 <hi>s.</hi> or 12 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard. This is the cauſe, I judge, that ſhort <hi>Spaniſh Wooll</hi> is ſo ſcarce here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if we conſider theſe things together, the dammage of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of one Pack from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>France</hi> at about 10 <hi>l.</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38421:4"/>12 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling, preventing the manufacturing of two Packs more in <hi>England,</hi> which would be worth 100 <hi>l. Englands</hi> loſs (in the whole) by the exportation of one Pack of <hi>Wooll</hi> can be little leſs than 60 <hi>l.</hi> It being generally combing-<hi>Wool</hi> (as before binted) that is exported to <hi>France,</hi> which makes Worſted, Stuffs, and Stockins: and beſides the advantage given them (as above aſſerted) by one Pack of rough <hi>Wooll;</hi> it's obvious to all Manufacturers, that a Pack of Worſted (or Cumbed) <hi>Wooll,</hi> worth 20 <hi>l.</hi> at 12 ſcore to the Pack, which is 20 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, and to make it more eaſie to every ordinary capacity; that in Stockins (to ſpeak within compaſs) A Pound of fine <hi>Wooll</hi> would make at leaſt two pair of Hoſe, worth 5 <hi>s.</hi> a pair, that is 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Pound of <hi>Wooll;</hi> or reckon thus, to ordinary Hoſe, three pair to a Pound of <hi>Wooll</hi> at 3 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d. per</hi> pair, come to the ſame ſum, and 12 ſcore Pound of <hi>Wooll</hi> making a Pack, ſo many pence for the Pound of <hi>Wooll,</hi> ſo many Pounds for the Pack, and a Pack of <hi>Wooll</hi> making 480 pair of Hoſe: which 12 ſcore Angels, being caſt up, is 123 <hi>l.</hi> without any reſpect given to the advantage given them in rough <hi>Wooll,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſerted.</p>
            <p>This, an inſtance for all, moreover, <hi>In it's firſt exportation,</hi> conſidering the Cuſtome when it is imported; the product of all theſe Charges augmenting the 100 <hi>l.</hi> when ſold there, laid out in another Commodity beyond Sea, the Cuſtom thereof being paid there, with Frait and Cuſtom (when imported) in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> it's much if it do not more than double the firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal.</p>
            <p>Now if ſo be, that the exportation of one Pack of <hi>Engliſh Wool,</hi> exported at 10 <hi>l.</hi> or 12 <hi>l.</hi> be neer 200 <hi>l.</hi> dammage to the King and Kingdom in general, by the conſequence; What will be the loſs of exporting 10. or 15 Thouſand Packs into <hi>France,</hi> beſides many to other parts (in two years time) is eaſily accounted (by ſuch) as are concerned in theſe Affairs: and although this Evil is almoſt incredible to many, yet it is too manifeſt, to ſuch as have made it (ſomething) their buſineſs to enquire into it; and not only ſo, but theſe further Inconveniencies muſt (by this means) ariſe upon us.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38421:5"/>
            <p>Firſt, The ſpoyling of our Trade with <hi>France</hi> in all our Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len manufacture, as doth already appear by the Impoſt put upon the ſame there, from 20 to 40 <hi>per cent.</hi> ſince the great quantity of our <hi>Wools</hi> is exported thither, whereunto woful experience may be a ſufficient witneſs.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, In time it will capacitate the <hi>French</hi> as well as the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (if not much better) to under-ſell our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Merchants in Forreign Parts, nay (poſſibly) in our own Country. To this, I ſhall only mention the words of a Merchant in <hi>Flanders,</hi> by Letters to another here, treating of this matter thus: <hi>We Engliſh have our Throats cut, with our own Weapons; wondering at the ſtupidity of the Engliſh here, that they ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, to poſſeſs the King's Majeſty with this deplorable and danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Caſe, in reſpect to the preſent and future Inconveniences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> By reaſon whereof, as in time the <hi>French</hi> will not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent our <hi>Engliſh</hi> manufactures to be ſold in <hi>France,</hi> but alſo bring theirs into <hi>England,</hi> and ſell them for four times the value here, to the great Inriching of themſelves, and the Impoveriſhing the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> only by new fantaſtick Fopperies; for which the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> pay not leſs than ſome Hundred Thouſands in a Year, to get themſelves into the <hi>French Mode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much indeed, have we been deceived (in this matter) to our ſhame, as well as to our apparent loſs; that, whereas in time of the Late War with the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> thoſe <hi>French</hi> Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets were thereby much prevented, many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Striped broad Cloths rent through into three parts (about 10 <hi>s. per</hi> yard, price) being put into the form of <hi>French</hi> Druggets, were ſold in each part at 8 <hi>s. per</hi> yard, and ſo in the whole came to 1 <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>s. per</hi> yard: So likewiſe it is certainly true, that many of thoſe Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets made in <hi>England,</hi> do go for <hi>French,</hi> and in order thereunto, directed to <hi>French Men</hi> in ſome of our Southern parts (from thence been conveighed into <hi>London,</hi> and there ſold for <hi>French Goods</hi>) to have coloured the buſineſs with the Cuſtom-houſe Officers, to ſave the Cuſtom of <hi>French</hi> Druggets: And this might have continued long, before the Cheat had been diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but being once found out by the Clothier (who could not (to his own private advantage) conceal ſuch an apparent injury to his Country) it was ſoon prevented: This I had an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38421:5"/>knowledg of, for the merchant beſpoke the ſame Goods of me. When I underſtood his end, I did refuſe to make the ſaid Druggets that he deſired me to make; whereby we may come to ſee (with clearneſs) the advantage that that people makes upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> fancies, by over-ſelling us in the ſame kind of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities that they make out of our <hi>Engliſh Wools,</hi> joyned (as before-minded) with their own; having alſo an advantage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by the cheapneſs of the Manufactors thereof, beyond what we can do; the <hi>French</hi> being very populous, and living harder than we can in <hi>England;</hi> as is evident by their Linnens, that, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Frait and Cuſtom, with profit to the Merchant, yet can be afforded cheaper than can be made in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſo it is, that the advantage we give them, beſides in the mixtures of our <hi>Wools</hi> with theirs, is ſuch, that, whereas their <hi>Wool</hi> of it ſelf is not worth 4 <hi>l. per</hi> Pack; being mixed with ours, becomes ſo fit for Worſted Stuffs, as that it comes to be worth no leſs than 12 <hi>l. per</hi> Pack. So that, all theſe things conſidered, it becomes obvious to every Eye, (that doth not (wilfully) cloſe it ſelf) that the exportation of <hi>Wools</hi> from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> is of a dangerous and deſtructive Nature to the very being of the Trade of this Kingdom. What ever Objections have been made thereunto (with reſpect to the Graziers preſent advantage) whoſe loſs may poſſibly be ſuppoſed (by prohibiting exportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to be about 20 <hi>s.</hi> in every Pack of <hi>Wooll</hi> that is ſo exported: In anſwer whereunto, I have this to ſay; That, though it may be granted, it will be ſo for a time in this particular Commodity; yet ſuch will (thereby) be the ſpoyl of the General Trade of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that what is gotten in one, will be loſt in every other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, as Corn, Beefs, and Muttons; on each of which with the <hi>Wools,</hi> the Graziers and Farmers advantage doth much more than equally depend; beſides the inevitable danger of the ruine of our Trade, and ſo conſequently, the ſtarving of our Poor, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome extraordinary means for their ſupport; who while the priviledge of our Trade is kept inviolate with other Nations, we have Money plentifully to expend for the advancement of the Farmers and the Graziers; for that is that which chiefly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Farmer and the Grazier, which is Fleſh and Corn, and not the quantity of <hi>Wooll,</hi> as will afterwards more fully appear.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38421:6"/>
            <p>And it hath always been obſerved (informer times) hitherto, that when the Clothiers have had the beſt Trade at <hi>London,</hi> the Farmer did not loſe his ſhare in the advantage thereof in the Country; according to the diſpoſe of Providence, Who hath ordered Nations, but more eſpecially, the People of every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in matters of this kind) to depend upon each other, and ſo to riſe and fall together, as they are deſigned, either to Mercy or to Judgment, by the hand of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, with a little deliberation, it will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appear, that the exporting of our <hi>Engliſh-Wooll,</hi> will not only prove the ſpoyl of our Merchants and Clothiers Trade, and ſo conſequently expoſe the <hi>Poor</hi> to deſperate ſtraits for <hi>ſubſiſtence,</hi> but in ſhort time muſt of neceſſity make the Country mens em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment (of every kind) to come to little, and ſo make them uncapable of paying Rent.</p>
            <p>For if it be ſo, that, while we have a little Trade, we can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly live one by another; What may be expected, if our Trade ſhould be taken away? Which is now in more danger by the <hi>French,</hi> than it hath been this 300 years paſt. And then we may conſider, what the price of <hi>Wooll</hi> may be in <hi>England,</hi> when we by our remiſneſs have loſt our Trade, by the skill and circumventing practices of Foreiners, and we helping forwards for a ſuppoſed profit; For there was not more art and skill in our Anceſtors, to bring home the work at firſt to the <hi>Wooll,</hi> and prohibiting the exportation thereof, and ſetling the manufacturing in <hi>England,</hi> than is now to export the Materials manufactured. The neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequence thereof, will be to bring the Price of <hi>Wooll</hi> (as it was 300 years agon, when moſt was exported) to be 6 <hi>d.</hi> a Pound, as appears in a little Piece, called, <hi>The Golden Fleece,</hi> (written by <hi>W.S.</hi> Gent.) in the Year,—56. Although the Cloth then made in <hi>Flanders</hi> of our <hi>Wooll</hi> at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, was ſold here in <hi>England</hi> at 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard; when at this day Cloth made in <hi>England</hi> of <hi>Wooll</hi> at 12 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, will hardly yield 7 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, which is above 30 <hi>per Cent.</hi> worſe to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade now, than it was to the <hi>Flemmings</hi> formerly.</p>
            <p>And though for the preſent, the price of <hi>Wooll</hi> be riſen by its exportation, yet if the quantity lately exported (being no leſs than 20 Thouſand Packs) had been kept in <hi>England,</hi> the quantity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38421:6"/>if not Ten thouſand Packs more would in time, have been expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the particular manufactures. For if the <hi>Woolls</hi> was not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to thoſe places beyond the Seas, there to be manufactured, they muſt of neceſſity have our Woollen manufacture, and then could not have thoſe advantages (as before hinted) by our <hi>Wools,</hi> to improve the <hi>French Wooll,</hi> and ſhort <hi>Spaniſh Wooll,</hi> and their fine-ſpun Linnens.</p>
            <p>By all which, it is ſo obvious, that in time to come, the <hi>Wooll</hi> in <hi>England</hi> would be much cheaper, becauſe by the aforeſaid means, leſs <hi>Wooll</hi> would be uſed in <hi>England,</hi> and beſides that which would be uſed, the manufacture would be ſo low, that it could not bear up any price (as is begun already in <hi>France,</hi> and will ſuddenly follow here in <hi>England</hi>) for it is generally reported, that <hi>Wooll</hi> is as cheap in <hi>France</hi> at this Day, as it is in ſome parts where it is uſed in <hi>England.</hi> And if it be ſo now, what in reaſon can be expected, as the effects of theſe two things? <hi>viz.</hi> The firſt, when the great quantity that is lately exported to <hi>France,</hi> with thoſe three Additions before hinted, that the Twenty thouſand Packs helps to work out, and eſpecially moſt making Worſted Stuffs, which goes as far by that means as forty Thouſand Packs of <hi>Wooll</hi> would if uſed in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it would be made more into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Cloaths, which conſums more <hi>Wool,</hi> than thoſe light and thin Stuffs do: which is a ſufficient Anſwer to that Objection, that the great quantity of any Commodity, that is exported, makes a ſcarcity, and ſo conſequently raiſe its price: the which I muſt confeſs, if it was a conſumptive Commodity, but it is quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this. For as our experience is, when the <hi>Wooll</hi> was all u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>England,</hi> (or very little exported) the <hi>Wooll</hi> was then at 18 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, and when all or the greateſt part was exported, it was at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound.</p>
            <p>The wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>What is, hath been;</hi> and, <hi>what hath been, may be again;</hi> and ſo no new thing.</p>
            <p>I ſhall make a ſhort Review of the Graziers and Farmers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent loſs: In the greateſt Commodity, which pays his Rent, as was formerly hinted. Suppoſe (through want of Trade) Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton be ſold at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Quarter the leſs, (which is but little) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 2 <hi>s. per</hi> Sheep, and there being ſome Sheep that 100. will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Pack of <hi>Wool</hi> (though ſome leſs) that comes to 10 <hi>l.</hi> which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38421:7"/>is the worth of the Pack of <hi>Wooll,</hi> (and ſo proportionably as to the Beefs) which is wholly loſt to the Grazier.</p>
            <p>And for the Corn (as I ſuppoſe) there may be about 50 <hi>ls.</hi> worth, (as far as I can judge in my Travels, to One Hundred Sheep throughout the Nation, which for want of a Trade, it may not (at ſome ſeaſons) come to Thirty or Forty at moſt, and if a good Trade, it may be worth Sixty or Seventy, by which means, it may eaſily be demonſtrated, how the Farmers come to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed.</p>
            <p>For the advantage of the Tenant conſiſts in the advance of the greateſt Commodity that payes his Rent, which is not in <hi>Wooll,</hi> but in Corn, Mutton and Beefs, and it is a neceſſary conſequence. That there being ſo many thouſand Families depending upon the Cloathing Trade (as was before hinted) that was inſtrumental to advance the price of the Corn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That where-ever Trade is, there People are moſt populous, and when thoſe perſons are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their Trade, depending wholly upon it, they muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably come to the Pariſhes, which is in many places begun already, and Daily encreaſed and feared in time, will ſo increaſe, that the Poor will be expecting more than there will be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to them. Although it be a Degreſſion, yet ſuffer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of one Pariſh; that when there was but ſome obſtruction to their Trade, by the Late Sickneſs, and <hi>Dutch</hi> War, the rate came for their Poor to Eight Hundred Pound <hi>Sterling</hi> in one Year, and I have been credibly informed, the Land to the ſaid Town, is not worth one Thouſand Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> and hapily one fifth part the dearer, becauſe of the Trade, as it is in all Cities, or Towns of Trade; than what can reaſonably be judged, when the Trade from ſuch a Town is wholly loſt, as is already in ſome parts in this Nation.</p>
            <p>To return to the Farmer, as being the emediate Perſon in this buſineſs, from hence may be concluded, that the Farmers Loſs for want of Trade, is fourfold greater then can be the advantage of the ſale to the tranſporter of <hi>Wooll,</hi> by (the exportation thereof unmanufactured.)</p>
            <p>I ſhall now endeavour to give ſome particular account how all are concerned; And before I do this, give me leave to inſert the Obſervation of a worthy Author Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38421:7"/>ſaith, <hi>That, then which was in King</hi> James<hi>'s Reign, about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand undreſt and undyed Cloaths yearly were Tranſported: whereby it was evident, that the Kingdom hath been yearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of about four Hundred Thouſand Pounds, which in fifty five years is near Twenty Millions, that would have been gained by the Labour of Poor Workmen in that time, which the Merchants gains for bringing in dying Stuffs, and returns of Cloaths dreſt and dyed, with other benefits to the Realm, beſides exceeding enlarging of Treffick, and increaſe of Ships and Mariners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There would have been gained in that time, about three Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by increaſe of Cuſtoms upon Commodities returned for Cloaths dreſt and dyed, and for dying Stuffs which would have been more plentifully brought in and uſed for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There hath been alſo tranſported in that time yearly, by Bayes,</hi> Northern <hi>and</hi> Devonſhire <hi>Kerzyes White, about Fifty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Cloaths, counting three Kerzyes to a Cloath, whereby hath been loſt above Five Millions by thoſe ſorts of Cloaths, in that time which would have come to Poor Work-men for their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, with Cuſtoms for dying Stuffs, and the Peoples profit for bringing them in with returns of other Commodities and Fraights for Shipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bayes are Tranſported white into</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>and being there dyed and dreſt, are ſhipped into</hi> Spain, Portugal, <hi>and other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, where they are ſold in the name of</hi> Flemiſh <hi>Bayes, ſetting their own Town Seals upon them; ſo that we loſe the very name of our Home-bred Commodities, and other Countries get the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Credit thereof. Lamentable it is, that this Land ſhould be deprived of ſo many above-mentioned Millions, as that our Native Commodities of Cloath, ordained of God for the natural Subjects, being ſo Royal and Rich in it ſelf, ſhould be driven to ſo ſmall advantage of Reputation and Profit to your Majeſty and People, and ſo much improved and intercepted by Strangers; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that God hath enabled and given your Majeſty power to advance dreſſing and dying, and Tranſporting all your Cloaths with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a year or two: I ſpeak it knowingly, to ſhew how it may be done laudibly, lawfully, and approved to be honourable, feaſeable, and profitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He obſerves alſo the increaſe of his Majeſties Cuſtoms, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38421:8"/>in and ſpending of dying Stuffs, as alſo ſtrength in Shipping, and ſetting ſo many thouſands of Poor on work; alſo noting, that in the Low-Countries, where theſe Cloaths are dreſt and dyed, they ſtretch them to ſuch unreaſonable length, contrary to our Law, that they prevent and foreſtale our Markets, and croſs the juſt prohibition of our State and Realm, by their Agents, and Factors, lying in divers places with our own Cloaths, to the great decay of this Kingdome in general, and diſcredit to our Cloaths in particular. Again, he adds, that if the accounts were truly known, it would be found that they make not clear profit only by Cloth Tranſported rough, undreſt, and undyed, Sixty Thouſand Pounds a Year; but it is moſt apparent your Majeſty, in your Cuſtoms, your Merchants in their Sales and Prizes,; your Subjects in their Labours, for lack of dreſſing and dying; your Ships and Mariners in not bringing in of dying Stuffs, ſpending of</hi> Alum (<hi>if not</hi> Copperas) <hi>are hindred yearly near a Million of Pounds: So that Trade is driven to that great hinderance of your Majeſty and People, by permitting your Native Commodities to paſs rough, undreſt and undyed. Thus Sir</hi> Walter Rawleigh.</p>
            <p>Now if it was thus with <hi>England</hi> ſo long agoe, when the Wooll was ſpun and made here into ſubſtantial Cloth; and that for want only of dreſſing and dying, many Millions were loſt to the King and Kingdom: What then hath been the loſs by ſo many thouſand Packs of Wooll exported (without any improvement,) eſpecially that to <hi>France,</hi> the conſequence of which, is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial (as hath been demonſtrated) than can be imagined (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting but one Hundred Pounds dammage by one Pack of Wooll,) of which there are not leſs than ten thouſand yearly, if not much more exported, by which there is dammage a Million of pounds <hi>ſterling,</hi> yearly to this Kingdome, (beſides the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Poor for want of Imployment) out of which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties dammage cannot be leſs than one Hundred thouſand Pound yearly: The leſſening of Shipping, and diſcouragement of Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; the Walls of this Kingdom hereby deſerve alſo to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>Next then to his Majeſties loſs, is that of the Merchant and Cloathier; after which muſt follow detriment to all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons depending on Trade, there being ſuch a Connexion of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38421:8"/>Trades one to another, and the whole of Trade being enlarged by the abounding of Laborious People. Thoſe ſupply the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Graziers with money, for to ſupply the Gentry. They again ſcatter it amongſt the Tradeſmen, as may be witneſſed by the building of the City of <hi>London,</hi> how Proviſion and all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive goods are advanced by it: by which circulation all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are either imployed, enriched, or both; and hence na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally comes Content, Harmony, and Pleaſure, one in another; the Poor being by Imployment delivered from fear of want, the Gentry, Merchant, and Tradeſmen, by the eſtabliſhment of Trade therein. This rationally is the ſtrength of any People, Poverty and Idleneſs bring their Shame and Ruine, which would unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably follow want of Trade. And ſo much the more where the greateſt Trade hath been; if it fails, the greater Poverty is and will be. And to inſtance, as here, in <hi>London,</hi> the Trade in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is the more, ſo by Conſequence it muſt be dear, and ſo beſt for all; ſo of the other hand, if the City ſhould be forced to keep ſo many thouſands, when all their work is done, as is now in the Building, it would be a great burden: ſo the caſe is in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in this particular, where great Trade have been formerly kept, and drawn ſeveral Families thither, and have raiſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities there; but when it fails, it is a miſerable ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition thoſe places are in. To return, in ſhort there is ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nextion and Dependancy one upon another in <hi>England,</hi> that if one fail, all the reſt more or leſs, either more near, or remotely are concerned; as in the natural body, when any Member fails, the whole ſuffers thereby; and as all Trades and Degrees of men may ſuffer by one failing in Trades, and in none more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. I will ſay then this of Wooll, as Merchant Articificers, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Sea-men, Fiſher-men, being the people, which by their ſtudy and labour do principaly, if not only bring in, or give occaſion to the bringing in of Wealth to the Nation, and other kind of people <hi>(viz.)</hi> Nobility, Gentry, Lawyers, Phyſicians, Schollars of all ſorts; Shop-keepers are they that receive from theſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute it again, and all are conſequently concerned in this rich Treaſure of Wooll, becauſe this being a Manufacture at home, ſets more hands at work than half the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38421:9"/>
            <p>May I not with modeſty and within Compaſs, ſay three parts of Laborious and Induſtrious People? Conſidering that moſt of the Shipping is imployed in this Affair, and alſo ſo many Trades that depend immediately upon this of Cloathing, that moſt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trades are but for Proviſion, either in Food or Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for Cloathing: and ſo from his Majeſty to the meaneſt, all are more or leſs concerned, <hi>The King moſtly;</hi> not only in that his People are by that moſt imployed and provided for, (nor in that ſuch a Staple Trade, the like whereunto the World hath not maintained with ſo good Advantage;) but becauſe ſo great a Revenue comes directly into him upon the Trade, occaſioned thereby: Thus as the King gains, or ſuffers moſt, ſo the perſons that have the greateſt Eſtates or Trades, and ſo all proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Beggar. And alſo conſidering that an accuſtomary thing begets ſuch an habit that is hard to reduce; as in our rough and undreſt Cloath to <hi>Holland,</hi> ſo it will be with all our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures in <hi>France;</hi> nay I am informed that the <hi>French</hi> hath not only impoſed a great Tax upon our Woollen Manufactures, from twenty to fourty <hi>per cent,</hi> but have alſo (as is affirmed, beſides that their Impoſition) abſolutely prohibited our Cloaths coming there. I am the more large in the Demonſtration of this affair, not only becauſe this hath coſt me many years labour and ſtudy to conſult all ſorts of concerned perſons, beſides mine own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience about it; nor becauſe it is ſo hard to convince people of the meaneſt capacity, but ſome of the wiſer ſort, how to cure this diſmal malady: which ſome deſpairing of, have rather thoughts of ſetting up ſome other Manufacture (in Lieu of endeavours to prevent the exportation of Wooll and Manufacturing of that at home, looking thereon as a thing not to be overcome,) as that of Linnens in ſome capable parts of <hi>England,</hi> and a better improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the product of Forreign Plantations, which may alſo be ſet upon together herewith as an Addition; ſo as ſeveral ſorts of Perſons maybe ſet better on work, not capable of this employment, and yet no prejudice to this of Cloathing: For all other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have the Advantage of <hi>England,</hi> or are equal to us in other Manufactures proper to their Countries, but not in this of Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and it will be found that all Trades in <hi>England,</hi> wholly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from this of Cloathing, bring not the tythe of Advantage that this doth.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38421:9"/>
            <p>Since men cannot rationally believe the effects to be greater than the cauſe, the moſt of other Manufactures either is in being, or brought to uſe, by the Manufactures of Wooll; even from the Farmer to the Merchant, all are concerned in this of Wooll; as may hereafter more appear. It now remains that we ſum up <hi>Englands</hi> Loſs by the Exportation of our Wooll to Forreign Parts; not only in the Advantage we might have by the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturing thereof, here in <hi>England,</hi> as formerly noted; but alſo in the importing of <hi>Dutch</hi> Cloath, and more in <hi>French</hi> Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, becauſe <hi>England</hi> improves not their own Wools; and of the humour of <hi>Engliſh</hi> people, in putting ſuch a value upon <hi>French</hi> Fancies, when themſelves are in a better capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if improved, to produce the like, or better, and ſave the following Sums.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. One Million of Pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> yearly, in the Exportation of our Wooll.</item>
               <item>2. Five Hundred Thouſand Pounds in Rough Cloath, which is but half what Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> obſerves in his time.</item>
               <item>3. Many Thouſands of Pounds by the Importing of <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Woollen Manufacturies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And laſtly, the evil conſequences thereof in looſing our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which would be encouraged thereby, and are the ſtrength or Walls of our Kingdom, as more particularly doth appear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Having now diſcovered the Dammage it is to <hi>England,</hi> in the tranſportation of <hi>Wooll</hi> from the King to the meaneſt, I ſhall endeavour alſo to diſcover the methods how it is done; before I ſhall preſcribe a Remedy (for it is not enough to know Diſtempers, eſpecially ſuch that are ſo Conſumptive,) it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to know the Cauſe of theſe Diſtempers; or elſe the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Remedies will in time come to be a diſeaſe, as it is too much in this caſe at this day in <hi>England:</hi> Where the Cauſes are miſtaken, the Remedies are conſequently miſapplyed, whereby a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38421:10"/>diſeaſe in ſuppoſition becomes one in <hi>Fact;</hi> the methods or ways of this evils are—Firſt, in <hi>Rumny-Marſh</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where the greateſt part of rough <hi>Wooll</hi> is exported from <hi>England,</hi> put aboard <hi>French</hi> Shallops by night, ten or twenty men well Armed to guard it; ſome other parts there are, as in <hi>Suſſex, Hampſhire,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the ſame methods may be uſed, but not ſo conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. The ſame for Combed <hi>Wooll</hi> from <hi>Canterbury,</hi> they will carry it ten or fifteen miles at Night towards the Sea, with the like Guard as before; but for other parts it muſt be done partly by the Remiſneſs of the Officers of his Majeſties Cuſtoms, and eaſie Compoſition for the Forfeitures of the Bonds, as more ſhall appear anon.</p>
            <p>And then for Combed <hi>Wooll</hi> in other Parts, ſome is Shipped off from <hi>London</hi> for Bales of Drapery; nay ſome at <hi>Lime,</hi> and alſo at <hi>Exon,</hi> where there is ten thouſand Pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> weekly laid out in the woollen Manufactury, which is moſt for Workmens Wages: I know no place clear; and then another reaſon, why perſons are not detected, is, becauſe all the <hi>Wools</hi> that have been taken in thoſe Parts, where moſt hath been exported, have been ſuffered to go off at the ſame place after Judgments paſt, and by the Officers, to the ſame Perſons at a low rate, being under rated to thoſe very men that intended to Ship it at firſt: ſo that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is never like to be avoyded that way; only that which is taken, happily may be a little the dearer, to keep the Trade going; for I have enquired, and cannot underſtand, but of two parcels of <hi>Wooll</hi> that have been ſeaſed on in <hi>Kent,</hi> that have been uſed in <hi>England,</hi> but all ſent away, and ſo his Majeſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence is cheated, who keeps Servants at great Wages to prevent ſuch abuſes.</p>
            <p>And then another Cheat is under a pretence of <hi>Wooll</hi> from <hi>Hampton,</hi> to the Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Gernſey,</hi> and ſometimes from other Parts which is againſt the Law; for there is no <hi>Wooll</hi> to be exported to thoſe Iſlands, but only from <hi>Hampton,</hi> and that by Law ſhould be by weight: but now it goes by groſs, by the Pack when it ſhould be weighed, but I believe not one Pack in Ten is weighed, for three Packs is put into one. Then from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38421:10"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> which is the greateſt miſchief of all to <hi>England,</hi> and much increaſed ſince the Act was in force againſt Cattel, the <hi>Iriſh Wooll</hi> can be ſold as cheap in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> as it is in thoſe Places where <hi>Wooll</hi> is uſed in <hi>England,</hi> which is a great augumentation to us of prejudice for Foreiners to have our <hi>Wooll</hi> ſo cheap as we in <hi>England,</hi> having other Conveniencies to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work us, as formerly hinted. The ways there muſt be by the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs of the Officers, in not taking ſolvant ſecurity and exactneſs in the weight of <hi>Wooll,</hi> and true examination of the returns of their Certificates, and partly by eaſie Compoſitions, if not before Bonds are forfeited, and happily much Combed <hi>Wooll</hi> there packt up as before, as Bales of Cloath, or Barrels of Beef, and Shiped as <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cloath; and in all points ſo cunningly carried, as they are ſeldom diſcovered, and never Sealed, as the Statutes in that caſe made and provided, do ſtrictly require.</p>
            <p>Here ſee what <hi>W. S.</hi> faith: <hi>Now to ſhew you more particularly theſe abuſes, how the Laws are croſſed and daily obſtructed to ſuch as endeavour to ſerve their Country, by ſuch as ought to encourage the Perſecutors; ſure there will be very many practiſes of evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents diſcovered; for firſt in the Cuſtom-Houſe, where Bonds are taken, to the intent that theſe prohibited Commodities paſs not by means of Mariners out of the Nation, but only from Port to Port for accomodation of ſuch Parts as want ſuch Commodities; they are very Remiſe and careleſs in taking of the Sea-mens diſcharge of their Obligatory Conditions; where alſo it is uſual with the Sea-men to bring fraudulent Certificates, and ſo to cheat the Kings Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, who keeps Servants at great wages purpoſely to prevent ſuch abuſes; or if there be a regular return of their Bonds, yet there is commonly a fraudulency in giving them, for the Maſters of Ships will ſo continue their deſigne, as he who is Maſter at giving the Bonds,</hi> and is legally bound, ſhall immediately paſs his Intereſt to another man, who taking charge of the Veſſel and Voyage, is notwithſtanding not engaged in the Poart Bond; and therefore, neither is he accountable for breach of their condition; <hi>Again, when the Port-Bonds are juſtly taken, and as juſtly returned; yet to prevent the true and real detection of the Offender, and to diſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38421:11"/>the legal Proſecutor, ſome Friends of the Offender will clap an Information againſt him, purpoſely to hinder and divert others, and ſoon after will let the Proſecution fall at his pleaſure; nay, it hath been ſaid, and peradventure not unjuſtly, that ſuch preventing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations have been antidated to the over-throw of the real Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; but when all is granted, and a full and formal hearing, and decree paſſed to the juſt condemnation of the Offender: Yet when judgments and inquiries are granted, and do without Errours of the Clarks (which is not always,) impower the Sheriffs and their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs to ſee Execution thereof made; it is familiar with thoſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to return a</hi> Non eſt inventus, <hi>or a</hi> Mortuus eſt, viz. <hi>Not to be found, or dead, even then when the Offenders and the Officers have been known to have been drinking together, at that very time when the</hi> Writ <hi>ſhould have been executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After all this, one ſtep farther will ſhew how Charity it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſeth Juſtice; for let all the former Proceedings be granted, and be candid, and clear, and that the Law be indeed juſtly and legally exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted; the Offender in cuſtody, and nothing remaining; but that he honeſtly diſcharge himſelf with money, ſeeing Bail will not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; nevertheleſs upon a lamentable Petition, and urging a great charge of Children to the Bench, the Offender is uſually admitted to compound for Ten in the Hundred, or leſs, when by his offence he hath gained a Hundred for Ten, or more, and peradventure hath undone a hundred Families or more in ſo doing: Yet all this while the honeſt Proſecutor, the only man that appears for the good of his Country, who ought by the Law to have the full benefit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Law</hi> gratis, <hi>it being enough that he ſpend his time for the promotion of the publick Wealth, after it hath coſt him ſeveral great ſums of money, and large expence of time, to bring the Offender to Tryal and Conviction, is diſmiſſed with little or no ſatisfaction, unleſs he be rewarded with the brand of an Informing Knave: Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they who made theſe Laws for the benefit of themſelves and their own Country, did intend a more current and juſt paſſage towards them, than thus to be obſtructed and baffeled. Such abuſes as theſe made</hi> Theodoſius <hi>ſay, as it is Recorded,</hi> that a wiſe man did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38421:11"/>Injuſtice by hazarding his Wiſdome and Eſtate for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Nation; <hi>And therefore ſome have not ſpared to urge, that Cuſtoms and Impoſt, and Toles and Taxes might be taken away from honeſt laborious hazardous Trades and Adventurers, and be put upon litigious Suits at Law, and ſuch as make benefit of their corrupt breath, that is to ſay, upon ſuch Lawyers as abuſe their Clyants, and ſuch malicious Clyants as abuſe the name of a juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Defendent. Nor is the Loſs in theſe by their Tranſportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the injury, but when honeſt men well affected to the good of their Country, do detect theſe</hi> Caterpellars <hi>of the</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>who make ſo vaſt gain, as hath been denoted upon the materials ſo carefully prohibited, when they do endeavour by due courſe of Law to make ſtoppage thereof, and to have the Offender's puniſhed; ſo many are the evaſions, ſuch combinations and intereſt in the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who ought to puniſh the Offenders; ſuch favour have they in Courts of Juſtice, and deceptions in the Return of Writs, and in general ſuch affronts and diſcouragements as the deareſt Lover of his Country, or moſt intruſted in Trade, dares not attempt to prevent that miſchief which his eyes behold to fall upon his Nation, or which his own perſon feels to pick his Pocket.</hi> Thus far Mr. <hi>W. Smith. not to mention the very ſame things above aſſerted that I have met withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence its to be lamented, to ſee what the conſequence of thoſe things are, I did think to have propounded ſome things for Remedy, but time not permitting, muſt beg the Readers excuſe, only this by the way, that if there was never ſuch effectual ways propounded, yet if thoſe wayes and means was never made uſe of, it is but beating the Aire. For the Life of the Law lies in the practick part; For if there was more care in this buſineſs when leſs Law, then hath been ſince more, are extant; the Fault then cannot be for want of Law, but only the want of Faithfulneſs in impartiality, in the Execution of thoſe Laws: And this in ſhort is the principal Cauſe of the continuance of this evil pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Tranſportation of Wooll, and was very engenuouſly confeſt to me by ſome of the Tranſporters of Wooll within this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38421:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>few Dayes in theſe very words, <hi>viz. That if we had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted at firſt according to Law, we ſhould not have acted the ſecond time:</hi> For if the Tranſportors did but rightly conſider the danger they are in, they would deſiſt; for I dare ſay, although ſome may eſcape for a time, you may be met withal firſt or laſt, and then are expoſed to ruine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38421:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
